Help on function eigsh in module scipy.sparse.linalg._eigen.arpack.arpack:

eigsh(A, k=6, M=None, sigma=None, which='LM', v0=None, ncv=None, maxiter=None, tol=0, return_eigenvectors=True, Minv=None, OPinv=None, mode='normal')
    Find k eigenvalues and eigenvectors of the real symmetric square matrix
    or complex Hermitian matrix A.
    
    Solves ``A @ x[i] = w[i] * x[i]``, the standard eigenvalue problem for
    w[i] eigenvalues with corresponding eigenvectors x[i].
    
    If M is specified, solves ``A @ x[i] = w[i] * M @ x[i]``, the
    generalized eigenvalue problem for w[i] eigenvalues
    with corresponding eigenvectors x[i].
    
    Note that there is no specialized routine for the case when A is a complex
    Hermitian matrix. In this case, ``eigsh()`` will call ``eigs()`` and return the
    real parts of the eigenvalues thus obtained.
    
    Parameters
    ----------
    A : ndarray, sparse matrix or LinearOperator
        A square operator representing the operation ``A @ x``, where ``A`` is
        real symmetric or complex Hermitian. For buckling mode (see below)
        ``A`` must additionally be positive-definite.
    k : int, optional
        The number of eigenvalues and eigenvectors desired.
        `k` must be smaller than N. It is not possible to compute all
        eigenvectors of a matrix.
    
    Returns
    -------
    w : array
        Array of k eigenvalues.
    v : array
        An array representing the `k` eigenvectors.  The column ``v[:, i]`` is
        the eigenvector corresponding to the eigenvalue ``w[i]``.
    
    Other Parameters
    ----------------
    M : An N x N matrix, array, sparse matrix, or linear operator representing
        the operation ``M @ x`` for the generalized eigenvalue problem
    
            A @ x = w * M @ x.
    
        M must represent a real symmetric matrix if A is real, and must
        represent a complex Hermitian matrix if A is complex. For best
        results, the data type of M should be the same as that of A.
        Additionally:
    
            If sigma is None, M is symmetric positive definite.
    
            If sigma is specified, M is symmetric positive semi-definite.
    
            In buckling mode, M is symmetric indefinite.
    
        If sigma is None, eigsh requires an operator to compute the solution
        of the linear equation ``M @ x = b``. This is done internally via a
        (sparse) LU decomposition for an explicit matrix M, or via an
        iterative solver for a general linear operator.  Alternatively,
        the user can supply the matrix or operator Minv, which gives
        ``x = Minv @ b = M^-1 @ b``.
    sigma : real
        Find eigenvalues near sigma using shift-invert mode.  This requires
        an operator to compute the solution of the linear system
        ``[A - sigma * M] x = b``, where M is the identity matrix if
        unspecified.  This is computed internally via a (sparse) LU
        decomposition for explicit matrices A & M, or via an iterative
        solver if either A or M is a general linear operator.
        Alternatively, the user can supply the matrix or operator OPinv,
        which gives ``x = OPinv @ b = [A - sigma * M]^-1 @ b``.
        Note that when sigma is specified, the keyword 'which' refers to
        the shifted eigenvalues ``w'[i]`` where:
    
            if mode == 'normal', ``w'[i] = 1 / (w[i] - sigma)``.
    
            if mode == 'cayley', ``w'[i] = (w[i] + sigma) / (w[i] - sigma)``.
    
            if mode == 'buckling', ``w'[i] = w[i] / (w[i] - sigma)``.
    
        (see further discussion in 'mode' below)
    v0 : ndarray, optional
        Starting vector for iteration.
        Default: random
    ncv : int, optional
        The number of Lanczos vectors generated ncv must be greater than k and
        smaller than n; it is recommended that ``ncv > 2*k``.
        Default: ``min(n, max(2*k + 1, 20))``
    which : str ['LM' | 'SM' | 'LA' | 'SA' | 'BE']
        If A is a complex Hermitian matrix, 'BE' is invalid.
        Which `k` eigenvectors and eigenvalues to find:
    
            'LM' : Largest (in magnitude) eigenvalues.
    
            'SM' : Smallest (in magnitude) eigenvalues.
    
            'LA' : Largest (algebraic) eigenvalues.
    
            'SA' : Smallest (algebraic) eigenvalues.
    
            'BE' : Half (k/2) from each end of the spectrum.
    
        When k is odd, return one more (k/2+1) from the high end.
        When sigma != None, 'which' refers to the shifted eigenvalues ``w'[i]``
        (see discussion in 'sigma', above).  ARPACK is generally better
        at finding large values than small values.  If small eigenvalues are
        desired, consider using shift-invert mode for better performance.
    maxiter : int, optional
        Maximum number of Arnoldi update iterations allowed.
        Default: ``n*10``
    tol : float
        Relative accuracy for eigenvalues (stopping criterion).
        The default value of 0 implies machine precision.
    Minv : N x N matrix, array, sparse matrix, or LinearOperator
        See notes in M, above.
    OPinv : N x N matrix, array, sparse matrix, or LinearOperator
        See notes in sigma, above.
    return_eigenvectors : bool
        Return eigenvectors (True) in addition to eigenvalues.
        This value determines the order in which eigenvalues are sorted.
        The sort order is also dependent on the `which` variable.
    
            For which = 'LM' or 'SA':
                If `return_eigenvectors` is True, eigenvalues are sorted by
                algebraic value.
    
                If `return_eigenvectors` is False, eigenvalues are sorted by
                absolute value.
    
            For which = 'BE' or 'LA':
                eigenvalues are always sorted by algebraic value.
    
            For which = 'SM':
                If `return_eigenvectors` is True, eigenvalues are sorted by
                algebraic value.
    
                If `return_eigenvectors` is False, eigenvalues are sorted by
                decreasing absolute value.
    
    mode : string ['normal' | 'buckling' | 'cayley']
        Specify strategy to use for shift-invert mode.  This argument applies
        only for real-valued A and sigma != None.  For shift-invert mode,
        ARPACK internally solves the eigenvalue problem
        ``OP @ x'[i] = w'[i] * B @ x'[i]``
        and transforms the resulting Ritz vectors x'[i] and Ritz values w'[i]
        into the desired eigenvectors and eigenvalues of the problem
        ``A @ x[i] = w[i] * M @ x[i]``.
        The modes are as follows:
    
            'normal' :
                OP = [A - sigma * M]^-1 @ M,
                B = M,
                w'[i] = 1 / (w[i] - sigma)
    
            'buckling' :
                OP = [A - sigma * M]^-1 @ A,
                B = A,
                w'[i] = w[i] / (w[i] - sigma)
    
            'cayley' :
                OP = [A - sigma * M]^-1 @ [A + sigma * M],
                B = M,
                w'[i] = (w[i] + sigma) / (w[i] - sigma)
    
        The choice of mode will affect which eigenvalues are selected by
        the keyword 'which', and can also impact the stability of
        convergence (see [2] for a discussion).
    
    Raises
    ------
    ArpackNoConvergence
        When the requested convergence is not obtained.
    
        The currently converged eigenvalues and eigenvectors can be found
        as ``eigenvalues`` and ``eigenvectors`` attributes of the exception
        object.
    
    See Also
    --------
    eigs : eigenvalues and eigenvectors for a general (nonsymmetric) matrix A
    svds : singular value decomposition for a matrix A
    
    Notes
    -----
    This function is a wrapper to the ARPACK [1]_ SSEUPD and DSEUPD
    functions which use the Implicitly Restarted Lanczos Method to
    find the eigenvalues and eigenvectors [2]_.
    
    References
    ----------
    .. [1] ARPACK Software, https://github.com/opencollab/arpack-ng
    .. [2] R. B. Lehoucq, D. C. Sorensen, and C. Yang,  ARPACK USERS GUIDE:
       Solution of Large Scale Eigenvalue Problems by Implicitly Restarted
       Arnoldi Methods. SIAM, Philadelphia, PA, 1998.
    
    Examples
    --------
    >>> import numpy as np
    >>> from scipy.sparse.linalg import eigsh
    >>> identity = np.eye(13)
    >>> eigenvalues, eigenvectors = eigsh(identity, k=6)
    >>> eigenvalues
    array([1., 1., 1., 1., 1., 1.])
    >>> eigenvectors.shape
    (13, 6)

